welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
okay check-ins
I am 15% nervous just jump up to 17%
when I said that which is interesting
there's a sort of like a pain in this
area I have a story behind that and I
just feel really calm better than that
welcome to the Stowe wha
I am the Stewart of the stoah Peter
Lindbergh and the Stowe is a place for
us to cohere and dialogue about what
matters most at the knife's edge of this
moment and today we have a very very
special guest than a dear friend of mine
Jasna turbo wick probably past therefore
I was practicing yeah I won't even try
it again but um she's a trainee at the
monastic Academy and I'll let her
explain what the NASA Academy is and
she's been going on retreats there and
she's on a longer treat this time she's
there right now and today she's gonna be
talking about her experience about
living in the monastery during a
pandemic and beyond that I think I'll
just let yajna introduce herself in the
monastic Adam II and what she's gonna
talk about today how it's gonna work is
he has none will to share her thoughts
and then we'll open up to Q&A
I'll warm her up in the room with some
questions and if you have a question for
you and I just write it in the chat box
and I will call you to unmute yourself
if you want me to read on your behalf
just indicate that in the chat box as
well so that being said I will allow
everyone to unmute themselves and yes
the floor is yours
thank you
and it's Todorovic
um hi so my name is Jasna and I'm a
trainee at the Manassas Academy which is
a modern monastery based in Lowell
Vermont so we're a training center that
combines a lot of different modalities
training modalities and the way that I
like to think about it is that were a
training center for creating better
people that has been kind of my personal
experience of it and my my view of what
what I've observed from the people who
have gone through this program so we
combine traditional wisdom practices
Buddhism we have a head teacher who's a
Zen monk we're not a Zen monastery he
doesn't teach them but he is a Zen monk
so we do a lot of practices like
meditation like several hours of
meditation per day and we have we're on
a very strict schedule but we also
combine that with a lot of real-world
work because training for enlightenment
is very nice and good but if you're not
using that to enact real change in the
world then well then what are you doing
kind of and I had all sorts of things
that I was thinking about saying and
then there were it just kind of
ballooned and I decided that probably
the best thing to do would be to answer
questions rather than just trying to
talk for a long time I want to note that
so we have this Vermont location then we
also have a California location and I
did not realize that the California
location would be calling into this call
and they're all watching right now which
is a little nerve-racking hi guys
they're leaving
[Music]
so I think maybe it'll open it too I
don't know if Peter you had some
starting questions that you wanted to do
or if anyone who had any questions at
all and we can kind of weave the story
or a narrative through that yeah I can
ask a few opening questions and while I
ask guys another question is just feel
free to write it down in the chat box
and then I can call on you and you can
meet yourself so someone like myself who
sort of is like I like being a cowboy a
spiritual cowboy and do my own thing but
I'm also drawn to a monastic life so I'm
in the in-between space and I'm imagine
a lot of people like that too they like
their own independence the own way of
doing things but they want to have some
guidance in the monastery setting so
what would you say in order to once they
sell it but just to kind of give them
enough information so they can make the
wisest choice make the wisest choice
about whether this type of training
would be useful to them yeah hmm yeah so
I mean I don't want to make the claim
that it's for like absolutely everyone I
think that can be a dangerous dangerous
claim to make what I have found is that
so I have been connected with the
organization for about four years but
it's really only in the past year that
I've started doing more intensive
training and I was resistant for a long
time to you know doing it the way that
it is here because you know how do I
know that this is actually the best way
and this kind of sucks you know you have
to wake up early and if you do all these
annoying things you have to live with
annoying people and you have to just
like deal with it and like surely
there's a better way to do this and
maybe there is but the thing is while
I'm here the best way to make use of all
of this is to throw myself in and to
trust it for the duration that I'm here
and when I started doing that when I
started when I stopped thinking about
like oh this this thing is wrong if they
did it this other way then it would be
better I'm not going to trust this
organization until they do it this right
better way when I kind of this isn't
really
a way to convince people I suppose but
like when when I was able to set that
aside and say like okay well I'm here
and it is done this way and so I should
participate fully and get whatever I can
from this that really made a big
difference and the thing is it's not
like you come here and then you're stuck
here forever you come here and you do
the training and you leave at some point
maybe you're here for a week maybe
you're here for a year the longest
person who's been here has been here for
five years I think but really there is
that element of like yeah at some point
it was like a frustration at myself
where I was like why am I here if I'm
not throwing myself in like how can I
get the most benefit of this training if
I'm constantly second-guessing it you
know right and what transformational
experiences have you had being there and
ones that other people have had it's a
really hard one not because there isn't
an answer but because it's there isn't a
neat answer to it we prefer things not
to be neat here at the store so yeah no
that's that's fine I'm just taking some
time to to think of how to put it into
words because I mean I can talk about
you know specific experiences but that's
not actually the answering the spirit of
the question I think I think
the fact is that okay so I used to live
my life in a pretty nice way I you know
have good friends I had successful I
have a successful career you know I'm
close I'm close with people and close
with my family I enjoy my work it's fun
it's challenging it's nice
I work in software I've worked in
software for the past ten years and then
at some point through doing this
training and kind of coming out of it I
was living here
a year ago I was living here for two
months I was doing there the co-working
program here which is basically like you
come here you live on the schedule but
during the day you do your own work so I
did that for two months and when I left
let's try and think about what I wanted
to do next
and there's a way in which all of the
nice things that have been happening in
my life just felt like they weren't
actually moving me towards my quote
unquote highest aspiration I don't know
exactly what highest aspiration means
here but it's just like some sort of
some sort of meaning some sort of like
is is doing if I just live my life like
you know following my career and like
having nice friendships and like
enjoying myself is that what I want to
be doing and that's not it's not a bad
life it was it was very nice but there
is the sense that this sort of shift in
understanding that actually there can be
so much more to my life
and I can do so much more and and kind
of like almost this like my god why
wouldn't I
why wouldn't I just do more of this
training and like just become more and
more of a better person and engage in
the world more fully and really
yeah really move towards what feels
meaningful and good decide does that
answer the question I don't know
[Music]
I imagine some of it might come out
again because we have some excellent
questions coming in the chat box better
than what I could ask so yeah this might
be touching up a little bit but maybe
Travis if you can unmute yourself and
ask your question yeah you touched on
this a little bit yes no but how did you
come to practice at the monastic Academy
maybe you could go into more like how
you found it and what what kind of steps
did you take to introduce yourself to it
before kind of taking a deep dive into
it yeah totally
this is this story tends to surprise
people um so I learned of the monastic
atomy because I think I can see him
smiling because a very good friend of
mine who I was working with at this
company called interacts on we made this
brain sensing headband that read your
brainwaves and gives you real-time
feedback on what your brain is doing so
I had a very good friend there who one
day decided to leave and move to a
monastery forever and and I was like
what are you doing this is the weirdest
decision you've made so far like this
makes no sense your life is so good here
you're just running away like acquitted
please stay but he left and I was upset
and angry and maybe eight months later I
went to go visit him and I was very
skeptical of the entire thing I was just
like what is this cult that took my
friend away and I wanted to see if you
know he was still the same person and
like if these are people who I can trust
care of him so I came to visit for like
a day and a half and was pretty weird
it was a weird place and I got to have
breakfast with the head teacher because
when guests come generally they get to
have like tea or breakfast or something
with the head teacher and at that point
I had been meditating for maybe about a
year or so yeah maybe a little more and
I was kind of like I was convinced by
you know like the health benefits of
meditation it's like it's good for
mental health and all of that but it was
okay that's nice but like really a
monastery like that's it that's a bit
extreme so I talked with the head
teacher and it was the first time that
someone had actually been able to answer
my sort of skepticisms and my questions
and my hesitations about meditation in a
way that I was just like oh okay
yeah that's what seems reasonable so I
left and I was like okay this place it's
maybe not awful I don't know if I like
it but it's not it's not what I was
afraid of and then over the years I just
kind of kept visiting every once in a
while maybe like every few months but
like once or twice a year or something
each time for a little bit longer
because there was just like there was
something drawing me to it but it was
still pretty kind of like arm's length I
think
and over time I kind of I got to see I
got to make friends with some of the
people going through the program and I
got to see the changes that were
happening in them and the way that the
organization worked and like the I one
of the things that I was afraid of is
that there would be you would think of a
monastery as being something that's like
a very separate from the world and like
not impacted by it and not impacting it
which this organization is absolutely
not doing like the entire point of this
training is so that we can become more
effective people in the world and so I I
grew to to see that and trust it more
and then and what was it 2017 or 2018
one of those years
I spent a year working in the
cryptocurrency world and I was just like
I had a crazy year there's a constantly
travelling between different continents
like living as a nomad which was
beautiful but exhausting and I
completely burn myself out and then I
left that job and and I thought oh I
know the perfect place to go to kind of
like reset myself and it decided that I
would go to the mask Academy for two
months or well for some amount of time
which ended up being two months and that
was when I was doing the co-working
program and that was really when things
started for me where I was like oh
there's like this is a lot more than
just like better mental health this is a
really important really fundamental type
of training that I have never seen
anywhere else I mean I'm sure other
places do things like this but I had not
been exposed to anything like this and
and that was kind of when I realized
that at this point in my life this is
the best possible thing that I could be
doing and there's all sorts of other
things that you know would be
interesting and good and the thing is
that like hmm all those other things
that I want to do I can still do them
after doing this training that was kind
of my thinking at that point where it's
like I can do those things now or I can
like spend a year making myself into a
more badass person and then do those
things even better than I would do them
now and actually my thinking has since
shifted I mean that that is still true
but I actually now am believing the what
I want to be doing is more of this
training and trying to bring it and make
it sort of more accessible to more
people so I'm actually in the process of
creating a Canadian branch of the
monastic Adam II near Toronto very early
stages but yeah I basically became or
came to the conclusion or the belief
that this type of training is so
important and so vital and nothing else
seemed right now at least nothing else
seemed worthwhile thank you cool
so we have a lot of questions coming in
I'm going to use my discernment we're
not going to go in the order that they
came in and everyone might not have a
chance to ask their question so let's go
with the Nicholas you had two good
questions filled which one you'd like to
ask and feel free to ask it yes No thank
you so much for through Danielson's
podcast and anyway a couple of the
questions that I had and you feel free
to use your discernment to decide which
one you want to answer or both
incorporate them in the first one was
what is a day in the life of a trainee
at the academy maybe you were gonna go
into that anyway the second one is what
are the greatest challenges that you
have faced or are facing during your
practice and what changes have you
noticed in yourself and overcoming them
sure
so Dana life I can kind of go over
quickly and I also have a blog post from
about a year ago that basically goes
through the daily schedule and has like
pictures of the place and stuff so I'll
just go through it quickly now but if
you want more details I don't know Peter
if you're able to find that blog post
somehow and post it in chat or something
but we can figure that out
so daily schedule is start chanting at
4:40 a.m. are you writing this down what
why not yeah you can also find this on
the website but you're welcome to write
it down so start chanting 4:40 then at
5:30 a.m. is an hour of meditation and
during this time we also have interviews
with the teacher so what happens is that
one person at a time goes into the
interview room with the teacher and they
demonstrate or discuss their
just it's just it's a time to have
one-on-one time and it's really from
what I understand it's really different
for every person like at what that means
sometimes for me it's like actual
full-on discussions with the teacher
other times I just sit there quietly
breathing and demonstrating my practice
sometimes he'll ask questions and I'll
answer some plain words sometimes he'll
ask questions and I will just answer
with the way that I'm breathing which
might sound ridiculous it's really not I
promise um so that's 5:30 to 6:30 then
6:30 to 7:30 is the exercise period so
we exercise everyday you choose your own
exercises there's no like mandatory
specific thing that you need to be doing
but you do need to be exercising in some
way then it's breakfast for I don't know
40 minutes maybe
and then at I'll say 8:15 or something
is that right yeah it would finish we
start our workday so between that and
twelve thirty five we're just working
and that depends on like what people
what the individual roles are some
people are working on like buildings and
grounds and right now we're like
building a path from the zendo to the to
the main building or like doing laundry
or whatever people are doing marketing
communications we're in the process of
doing the engineering for the monastic
village which were building there's
gonna be like an area on the grounds the
where like people are going to build
their own houses and like live sort of
not doing them and asked of training but
living in a monastic community so some
people are doing communications around
that anyway so that's just l work period
12:35 is lunch is that right yeah 1:15
is a chore period for 45 minutes and
then between 2:00 and 5:00 is free time
except that there's a 30 minute period
within that free time where you need to
be doing Sutra study which is you're
basically like citing the ancient texts
so for half an hour every day but you
can choose when that is within that time
then right yeah
and then the evening from 5:00 until
6:30 is a different thing depending on
the day
sometimes we do more work sometimes it's
circling practice circling as a type of
authentic relating practice sometimes
will do trauma healing like bio emotive
I don't know if you're familiar with
that but that's one of the sort of
training modalities that we do here one
of the things that we do to help our
training is emotional clearing and
emotional processing sometimes we'll do
workshops sovereignty workshops or other
things sometimes will do embodiment
practices sometimes we'll do more
meditation so that's like the period
between five and six thirty is pretty
much different every day six thirty we
do group sutra study which is basically
one person presents something that
they've been reading about and then
there's like a sort of group discussion
about it 7:00 until 8:30 we do sitting
meditation again again with interviews
so people go and talk to the teacher I
think most of the time people get to
maybe not but you got to talk to the
teacher every day or two in general and
on retreat on full retreat weeks it's
it's everyday generally and then 8:30
p.m. we chant for about 15 minutes and
then it's bedtime and then so that's
that's called like responsibility weeks
so most of the month is a responsibility
period and then we have one week of the
month that is what's called the
awakening period who our people would
call it our retreats and the way the
schedule is different for that one is
just like replaced pretty much
everything with meditation your other
questions one was something about what's
the most challenging thing I think I
mean there's a lot that's challenging I
think one of the most challenging things
is and and the most beautiful things is
actually living in community because
you're living and training and working
and eating and everything with the same
people and you have conflicts and you
can't get away from them like one of the
reasons that actually this training is
so profound is that you can't get away
from your problems and you just have to
deal with them you can't like if there's
something you dislike you can't avoid
them because you live with them you work
with who's your trainer without you're
just you're around them and so there's a
really there's a real beauty to that
because you're committed to
um you're committed to loving and
supporting these people and still
clashing with them you know like it's
not it's not about like being you can't
protect you can only pretend to like
someone for so long you know so like all
the stuff comes out and you kind of
support each other through it and that's
really difficult and probably one of the
most growing experiences of this entire
place and it's one of the things that
makes a real difference between like
meditating on your own a lot and
meditating in community it's yeah thank
you and I guess it's the last thing what
what changes have you noticed in
yourself in overcoming that challenge of
living in community yeah that one I'm so
much more comfortable now just telling
people what I think or how I feel like
when I disagree with them about
something and it just doesn't feel like
that big a deal anymore it does
sometimes but like I actually distinctly
remember a time it was more than a year
ago I don't remember exactly when but I
remember time when like someone said
something to me and I just kind of like
smiled and it was like aha
and then internally I was like what like
I completely disagree with everything
that you're saying but like I don't know
like I'm just I'm feeling a couple of
the situation and want to leave like I
was internally my experience but
externally I just kind of like smiled
and pretended whereas now that seems
like not even a thing like it's just
easy for me now like when someone says
something I think should be like oh I
disagree with that
or like that that bothers me for like
this in this reason it's not like some
sort of like clash or conflict it's
actually just
sort of like lowering that resistance of
like
the the disagreements are okay that like
judgment is okay it's okay for me to say
like hey I'm judging you right now or
like I feel unsafe with you right now or
something like that and I can trust that
that's actually going to be received in
in a certain way and that that person is
going to want to like be with me in that
interaction and or maybe they won't
maybe they will have their own freak out
and walk away and then like we'll deal
with it later or something so I'm good
mm-hmm sorry I'm parsing this as
toggling or or reducing the opacity of
the membrane between your inner world
and your outer experience that's great
that's a great way contributes to a
greater authenticity yeah it's really
cool some great questions coming in
change has had one which I'm personally
curious about I yeah I'd like to ask
about the experience of living in a
monastic lifestyle what lessons can the
general public take from that about
living in lockdown and and then the
further becomes a change in our lives
once we come out of lockdown and after
coab it 19 is no longer the huge problem
that it currently is I'd really like to
hear about what what lessons do you
think we could take yeah I think one of
the
biggest things so there's a couple of
things that I think are really have been
extremely useful and beneficial for us
in living through this crisis and I'll
say actually we got infected with Kovac
in early March so we like that that went
through the monastery where all everyone
is fine but one of the really beautiful
things about it is the fact that we live
in community and so we were able to take
care of each other
and so much of what is happening right
now is that people are isolated alone in
their homes and we have you know
beautiful things happening like people
are zooming so much more I'm talking to
my family so much more than ever before
which is really lovely but there is
something really profound about the fact
that we were living in community we
didn't have to feel that extreme
loneliness that I think a lot of people
are feeling right now and I think that
it really it speaks to I know that
there's a lot of people who really like
the idea of community living you know
like creating like shared community
houses or like little villages with all
your friends and stuff but I think it's
really coming a lot more alive for
people now from like what I've seen the
discussions that I've seen online
everyone is not everyone but a lot of
people are saying like let's you know go
to a communist let's build our own thing
and monasteries are really like a model
of that they're a model of a community
living together and then the other thing
well yeah so I mean I think for that one
just more concisely is basically like
living in community has a lot of really
important benefits and at a time like
this it's especially important and you
know when certain people were very sick
there were other people who are less
sick were able to take care of them
rather than people just kind of being
cooped up at home the other thing is
that throughout all this we were still
like we were we shifted our schedule a
bit so that we could like Cameron get my
regrets and stuff but we were still
practicing every day for several hours
meditating
and it really I think helped us stay a
lot more grounded and a lot more able to
process the information without not to
say that like we weren't going nuts
because in many ways we were
but it really was beneficial to have
like a strong meditation practice and
the thing is during that time specially
our teacher was really guiding us to
deal with the problem of death you know
this is what all of us are facing right
now the fact that we're going to die
that the people who we love are going to
die and that's a really hard thing to
face and the entire world right now is
facing that and what contemplator
ditions or at least buddhism does
largely or not largely but in a very big
way is make you face your own death make
you face your mortality make you face
the fact that you're gonna get old that
you're gonna get sick that everyone you
love will die and I'm laughing because I
just like remembering some of the
meditation some of the guidances that
our teacher did or like literally we
would sit for an hour and contemplate
death and so we use this opportunity to
really because you know it's happening
anyway you're you we're dealing with the
fact that we're gonna die or maybe we're
not dealing with it
but we're facing the fact that we're
gonna die so we might as well you know
step in and do it fully so that was I
think another another thing that was
really important about living nastily
is the fact that we were able to do that
I'm thinking of some other things but
they're kind of like half form so I
think I'll leave them for now cool Tonya
you have a question yeah I was just
wondering because you're starting this
maple up in Canada what what was the
sort of
what stirred you to do that what
motivated you and if there is a vision
there or yeah and and there's the second
part of the question when you're talking
about the the day-to-day things that
come up when people are living in close
quarters and can't get away from each
other yeah how and I'm just curious what
questions and learning has come up for
you withholding whatever is motivating
you and and then that day-to-day reality
yeah so for what motivated me it was a
little bit of a snowball effect I came
back from the monastic Academy so I was
here for two months and then I left and
I knew that I wanted to come back for
more training but it wasn't the right
time for me at that point there was some
family things that I wanted to do in
Toronto for a little while and it was
just kind of like thinking about what I
wanted to do next and I didn't at that
point I didn't have a place to live
because well coincidentally I had moved
out of my apartment a few months earlier
and because I knew that it was going to
come back to the monastic atomy I kind
of didn't want to find like a one-year
lease somewhere or something like that
and then I thought well if I buy a place
then I can at least I can like rent it
out while I'm gone and not like it was
all just like a bunch of like logistical
stuff and then I was like wait I can buy
a property somewhere outside of the city
which would be really lovely and I had
been living nomadically for a year
before that anyway so living outside of
the city wasn't that different from just
like you know constantly traveling or
something just as far as like seeing my
friends in the city uh-huh and then it
was like oh I could I could places in
the city are a lot more expensive than
places outside of the city and so I
started looking at places like oh I
could actually get a pretty big place
and
at some point in the future something
will magically happen and people from
the mask Academy will want to expand to
Canada and then I can give them this
this property right this is this
location they can they can do it there
and then very quickly it was like
they're not it's not gonna be them
magically doing it I'm gonna write I
should just like start that process and
I was like renovating it to be like the
right thing and it was just like kind of
just taking one step at a time and then
each thing snowballed and then
eventually eventually it started
becoming a real thing and I was like
well I can definitely be like the
executive director of this like I'm
capable of doing that but I had this
conversation with my with my teacher and
it was like well I'm a NASA Academy
needs a teacher so who's gonna be the
teacher and I was like oh well not not
Oh cuz I mean I already knew that that
was a thing but I was like oh I see so
there's no one so I'm the only option
I'm a terrible option but you can train
me and maybe someday I will be able to
be a teacher and maybe not I don't know
but we basically came to the agreement
that the thing that would make sense is
for me to do a lot more intensive
training and move towards becoming a
teacher but the whole thing really
started with like I don't want to find a
place to rent and and every step of the
way it felt like the right thing but it
was it was very much like there's a lot
of different directions that this could
go in and I'm just gonna I'm not gonna
worry about it too much I know the
general direction that I want and I'm
gonna like start taking steps in that
direction and it's gonna end up
somewhere else but that's fine and it's
been incredible like it's it's this
community has formed around it that is
just mind-blowing like there's people
who hear about what I'm doing and just
like jump in and want to help and like
I'm yeah like I I don't actually don't
understand how to process how you know
quote-unquote successful it's already
been in in that
this this big community has already
formed around it and and and so many
people are helping in so many ways and
then we're not actually sure how to tie
you into your second question I don't
know if you want to maybe ask it again
feels like you're starting to describing
the experience that's been emerging that
you've been having with people on the
ground yeah yeah I mean my experience
has basically been that like if I if I
just read if I believe in this thing and
I just like take steps towards making it
happen
other people get excited about it too
and then they take steps towards making
it happen and like I don't I'm not
necessarily wanting to make it just like
this thing that I want it to be I want
it to be like co-created by the
community um so yeah that part has been
just mind-blowing to me honestly cool
Megan you had a few questions I'll try
to link some of my questions with others
that I've read that I think are related
I was interested in whether you felt
maple could fit under the engaged
Buddhism movement I kind of want to link
this to other people asking around like
impact of maple and how you view their
theory of change and if there's other
ways of impact that they conceive of
that's both like political but also
beyond social and political change which
is kind of how I understand engaged
Buddhism and then my second question you
can answer either/or was just around
your earlier comment about this like
Frank radical honesty you've been able
to cultivate and how you kind of have
lost reservation just speak your truth
and I was just curious whether you ever
felt that
refraining from sharing what is honestly
coming up for you can be a kinder more
compassionate thing to do sure yeah so I
mean I'll answer the second one first
and yeah definitely it's not it's not
just about like being unfiltered so in
Buddhism there's this thing called the
Eightfold Path which you know you and I
have talked about a little bit and one
of the things in the Eightfold Path is
right speech and right speech does mean
being truthful but it also means like
saying things at the right time and
saying things kindly and it also means
other things but I think one of the
things about doing this type of training
is that ideally over time you start
becoming less reactive and so it
actually becomes a lot easier to talk
about like the difficult things that are
coming out or the disagreements or
something like that because you're not
necessarily saying them from an angry
place if the reaction that you're having
is anger just using that as an example
and so there is a way to speak your
truth without that necessarily being
some sort of difficult or traumatizing
experience for the person who's hearing
it um not that you can you know control
everything about how someone will
receive it but yeah I definitely don't
want it to come off as like always just
blurting out whatever is on your mind
and being like yeah I'm practicing
that's not exactly the point and so then
for the first question I've heard a bit
about engaged Buddhism but I don't
really know like the definition of that
that's a tip not Han thing right yeah I
like I guess he's the recent person he's
been advocating it but
it comes from a I think a history of
Buddhists who wanted to reclaim the
political power that some scholars at
least have claimed was stripped after
the Cold War era and when brought to the
west the DC politicization of Buddhism
was seen as one of the outcomes I
suppose mm-hmm okay so I don't have a
lot of the academic background on that
so like I can kind of answer in some
sort of like my own interpretation
interpretation of things but yeah I I
feel like my answer won't quite be like
satisfying exactly the question as
opposed but I think if I take the
question more broadly as like what is it
that maple is actually doing that is
making a difference in the world all
right
so I mean there's you know there's like
the specific easy things to point to or
like when we go to protests or something
or the causes that we support and things
like that but that's actually the less
interesting stuff I think although
that's important too but the way that I
see it is I want to be careful about how
I put this a lot of our problems in the
world start a lot earlier than we think
and the tree
that we're doing at maple part of it at
least is in trying to look at the
foundations of where our problems start
so part of why the meditation practice
is so important is that you kind of you
still everything over time and then you
start to see like all the little things
that are urging you towards doing
certain things making certain decisions
that like are very easy to rationalize
but are actually like something much
more subtle that's happening in your
mind and basically by changing this
foundation we change we change ourselves
like by doing this practice you change
yourself into being someone who is able
to function from a more I don't to say
grounded place because it's not exactly
it but a more wise place a less reactive
place and everything snowballs from
there all the little decisions that you
make turn into big decisions and you
know the way that we live our days is
the way that we live our lives and and I
don't mean to say that like it's
completely impossible or like the only
thing we need to be doing is working on
ourselves and that will change the world
like there we have to be working you
know bottom-up and top-down we have to
be looking at the system's level things
but I do personally believe that so I'm
just trying to
two great words here you know how
there's like we can do like all sorts of
like brain games and stuff to like make
a maker make our brains better you know
if you do don't goo puzzles and that
makes you be better at math and better
at focusing and whatever else there is a
more fundamental type of training that
we can be doing and we can basically
create ourselves into people who have
minds that like the types of minds that
can actually solve problems without
creating new ones or at least making
fewer new ones and so that's that's one
way of looking at it looking at a little
bit more abstractly one of the things
that we talked about here at maple is as
these three pillars of wisdom love and
power and we will often say is that the
people who have wisdom and love often
don't want power and people who have
power often don't have wisdom and love
and so what we're trying to do is train
leaders who are wise loving and powerful
so which might mean taking people who
are powerful and building out their
wisdom and building up their love or it
might mean taking people who have wisdom
or yeah I have some wisdom have some
love and giving them more power and so
part of like the sort of more practical
stuff that maple does is actually
empower people to do a lot of things
first within the organization like we
are we're nonprofit and so people have
to have all sorts of roles within the
organization someone will be doing
fundraising will be doing bookkeeping
kitchen management all that and so like
people will come in and but not have
certain real-world skills and then those
that they get built up and they actually
are put into leadership positions where
they're completely out of their depth
like we put people into positions where
they will basically
not necessarily fail but they will
struggle and failure is okay struggling
is okay they're supported all through it
but it's basically like getting that
type of real-world training in addition
to the contemplatively and like really
like holding those two aspects together
that's why we talk about awakening and
responsibility like those are two
pillars of maple that like one side is
not enough you have to actually be
building up both and they have to be
informing each other let's see here okay
so you leap you could ask your question
you had a few I think thank you I was
just typing out another one right now
[Music]
yeah which one I want to go for so I'm
gonna lift them up and hop oh you just
asked one because we don't have much
time so jerk yeah yeah
yes then can you tell us a little bit
about best practices and monastic
philosophy on how to deal with the
uncertainty of how much time you should
be spending between on training yourself
to become a more badass person and then
putting that bad ass to work so you're
gonna probably go through a cyclical
check-in process to say okay I needed
more training at this time I got more
training now I can go do some stuff I'm
doing some stuff I'm noticing I could
probably use more training how do you
balance that what are the checks to make
sure that yeah this is working for you
is this a solo journey for you or does
the monastic practice help to people
there help tell us about that please
yeah it is absolutely not a solo journey
and it can't be I think so like even as
you were saying your question like your
question is how do you know when these
certain things happen or when you need a
certain thing and
the first thing that was coming to mind
was like I mean there is a way in which
I can you know make those decisions and
maybe they'll be right and maybe they'll
be wrong but having a teacher is
actually a really really vital part of
doing this and that's it that's a hard
thing because like having that type of
trusting relationship with someone is
very difficult and it like it took me
years to actually be able to trust so
are you the head teacher here enough to
you know step into full training with
him um but there really is that level of
trust were like I actually I mean he's
been doing this for a long time and he
is like I I do actually cross his wisdom
in in guiding me along the right path
and so some some part of it that is just
like find someone who is better than you
and like half of them tell you you but
and like I do mean that and also I know
that that's like not really how it can
always be some of it is honestly just
informed by necessity probably it would
be better to just like if I could take a
month or three months or something and
just meditate probably I will probably
that would be more useful than me doing
anything else for those three months I
do genuinely believe that but that's not
really feasible you know like I still
have to be working in the world I still
have to be helping the organization and
all of that so some of it really is just
informed by what is it that needs to
happen
um what is it that I need to do to like
maintain my livelihood and that's
actually a really good question because
a lot there's actually a lot they can
follow away that we think can't but one
thing that
is it that he said I'm gonna I mean I'll
butcher it so I don't know if this is
exactly what's already said but he said
something along the lines of like if
you're spending more time on social
media than you are listening to Dharma
talks then social media is your teacher
like that is and like that's just a
statement of fact I think like the thing
that you surround yourself with is the
thing that's going to influence you the
most the people that you surround
yourself or the people are going to
influence you the most and so like in my
view if I want to be a specific type of
person then I need to surround myself
with other people who are working
towards that as well and that like it
can't be a lonesome journey you cannot
you could do that on your own but why
would you like it's it's so much harder
so I don't think that actually fully
that answers your question
exactly as posed but I think that's the
answer that I have I'm thankful for it I
do have a really burning follow-up Peter
thumbs up if that's okay thank you you
know in thinking about how we can
construct ourselves it at least appears
to me at very least that monastic
practices are taking age-old wisdom on a
whole slew of different ways of
improving yourself right you can change
your social context you can change your
social ties you can change your basic
physiology and how much your exercise
how much you sleep what kind of postures
you sit in how comfortable is your brain
with comfort and discomfort
how does it feel about things with types
of neural patterns are you encoding and
practicing what are you building up
right and so because and and there is
there is an enormous enormous amount of
wisdom in these practices but I wonder I
mean what are their I guess my question
for you is are there also more modern
insights that you're aiming to draw from
and in particular not for the sake of
being modern but obviously for the sake
of you know how is it that life today is
very is different in a specific way that
means you have to tweak you have to take
the kind of training you're doing in
order to actually yeah get optimal
flourishing out of the human
as you improve one sure yeah so I mean a
lot of the practices that we do here are
actually not ancient
so like circling is a big one circling
is sometimes we call it social
meditation but it's basically like
there's this quote I think by around us
that's if you think you're enlightened
go spend a week with your family
select the fact is like there is some
way to you can be like blissful and
wonderful and things can be great when
you're sitting alone on the cushion but
that's really put into practice in
relationship and so we do these circling
practices together to kind of like
really test out that our ability to be
present with each other and with
ourselves and so this is a much more
modern thing I don't remember once our
claim came about I think I want to say
in the 90s and there's emotional
clearing stuff the bio motive practice
[Music]
we are as human beings in this modern
world carrying around so much emotional
trauma like lowercase T and in many
cases uppercase T we are extremely
impacted by things and then kind of not
processing that you know you kind of
just like hold yourself together as a
set yourself up can keep going and this
is really like makes it extremely
difficult to go through life and be
happy but we kind of just do it as a
society so much that we don't actually
quite realize it and so emotional clear
anger and like emotional processing type
things have I think are extremely vital
practices that are much more modern I
don't I don't want to say like people
and the past didn't need them I don't
know what it was like at that point but
that's sort of one of the more modern
things that that we're pulling in and
then I talked a bit about how like we're
placed in different
within the monastery like this is we're
basically getting like business type
training and you know startup type
training and then this is the type of
stuff that really is necessary if you
want to actually go out into the world
and do things ever because you can't
just be a monk who is completely
separate from from everything that's
going on in the world you might become
wonderfully enlightened and then what if
you don't know how to you know keep
books or like have I don't know
conversations does that kind of answer
your question yeah thank you
cool so we're at the hour mark so we're
going to end questions there before I
make any closing thoughts yeah do you
have any final statements of anything
really so if you want to I do have that
blog post from a while ago that talks
about like daily life at the monastic
academies that people are interested in
that they can seek that out
there's the emerge podcast which is
hosted by one of the monastics here some
of the episodes in that also go into
[Music]
things about monastic life not many of
them but some I think the most recent
one was an interview with our head
teacher so that one is really quite
wonderful I recommend to listening to
that one there's a paper that a past
resident wrote for I think his master's
thesis
it's called monasteries of the future
that one's really interesting if anyone
is interested in looking that up our
website no wait it's oh no Vanessa
Academy don't work I posted one this is
common I hope that's the right one and
click on it and see I don't know
maybe just Google Tasks Academy both of
them work I think I'm not sure which one
redirects to the other oh great san-chan
just posted a great blog post by another
monastic here called touching that's all
that's coming to me right now I'm on
Twitter and if people have more
questions
ooh I don't wanna make that promise
because I don't actually have that much
free time here but like I was gonna say
if you have more questions ask me on
Twitter but I don't know that I will
actually be able to answer them but feel
free to ask them and I'll try to try to
get them we have everyday we have three
hours of free time the rest of the time
is all structured and Monday's are free
days so those are the times when I can
actually do non monastery things very
cool so I'll make some closing
announcements in a moment but Jasna
thanks so much for coming on today
it was greatly appreciated and hope to
have you back and we'll double click on
that discussion now maybe cool this down
the colleges for five more minutes after
every chat be brief so upcoming events
you can go to the website the stove dot
CA we have about we have a wisdom gym
here recurring events happens every week
live about 11:00 so far so you can just
check it if you have like sir credit
speed-dating extra special dance parties
freestyling through a pandemic
breathwork
stoic breath lots of cool stuff you can
RSVP there also on meetup.com yeah our
super than website for now we also have
a one-off events we only have three this
week the next one is human systems
live-action redesign that's on April
30th there's a Thursday right yeah
Thursday at 2:30 p.m. Eastern Time so
Joe edelen's human systems team and
they've you sort of like the foundation
of meaning the atoms of meaning our
values and has a very unique
understanding of values and a unique
process and methodology to understand
the values of a system that are being
lived by and not lived by and how to
redesign a system so if you have any
systems you want to redesign definitely
double click on that session I took
their course it's amazing and that being
said the Stowe is based on a gift
economy I view it as a gift for all of
us to use in this time of need
if you're inspired to give a gift to the
stoah and the gifts could be anything
really you just go to the website and
check out the gift economy at the bottom
of page all right
thanks everyone greatly appreciate it